JENNIFER WANJIKU KINYANJUI

Email: jennifer.kinyanjui.n@gmail.com P.O Box 73923 – 00200 Nairobi, Kenya Tel: +254 723 175 820 / +254 722 347 544

I am a seasoned Human Resource professional with 10+ years' of experience working with Organizations operating in Africa and Asia regions. I have led Resourcing and Talent Management functions and partnered in the alignment and implementation of the human resource strategy to support the business objectives. In addition, I have supported various Organizational Development initiatives including; development of HR Policies and Procedure; Talent management framework and Succession planning; Competency framework; Job family modelling, Redesigning of organization structures and conducting job evaluations.

WORK EXPERIENCE

July 2019 to date: Talent and Resourcing Manager G4S

In this role, I lead the Talent management and Resourcing function within Kenya and work closely with the Group office in the UK and the Africa Regional office to ensure compliance and alignment to the Global Business.

- Devise and implement a talent management strategy in line with the Group guidelines
- Align the recruitment and selection processes, performance management and development strategies to the to the Group and G4S Kenya competency framework
- Support in the formulation of a succession planning framework for the G4S Kenya Business in line with the Group level practice.
- Liaise with the Regional office and Kenya management to ensure the current staff complement the succession plans in place
- Develop a talent inventory and address existing gaps and ensure alignment with the business objectives
- Lead the development of recruitment and retention strategies in line with the Group practice.
- Manage the resourcing initiatives across the G4S Kenya Business
- Build and implement a sustainable Employee Value Proposition in line the Group guidelines to position G4S Kenya as employer of choice
- Oversee the vetting process for staff and contractors conducting business within the G4S Kenya Business
- Liaise with the Business units on business planning and budget formulation on resourcing across the business
- Reporting to the management on Talent management, Resourcing and vetting on a monthly, quarterly and annual basis

November 2013 – July 2019: People & Organizational Development Manager International Livestock Research Institute (ILRI)

Countries of Operation: Africa (Kenya, Uganda, Tanzania, Ethiopia, Zimbabwe, Mali, Nigeria and Burkina Faso)

Asia (India, Pakistan, China and Vietnam)

This is a blended role where I led the Resourcing function and worked closely with specific research programs at the HQ in Nairobi and Regional offices in Africa and Asia to partner in the implementation of the Human resource strategy and support staff through the full employment cycle.

Key Achievements

- ✓ Contribution to the development of:
 - Diversity and Inclusion policy
 - o Talent management and Succession plan framework
 - o Competency Framework, Job families model and Career paths
- ✓ Developing and implementing Service Level Agreements (SLAs)
- ✓ An increase in Applicant pool for positions with exceptional skills through active sourcing, networking and headhunting
- ✓ Carried out a Skills and Cost analysis of the Consultancy Contracts worldwide
- ✓ Developed a Consultancy management guideline / policy
- ✓ Review of the Recruitment policy
- ✓ Contributed in the identification of an ideal recruitment system for the Organization (WIP)
- ✓ Initiated the adoption of Assessments & Psychometrics in the Recruitment and Talent management processes

Strategy and Work force planning

- Work closely with the Director, People & Organization Development, Senior managers and other key stakeholders in designing a talent acquisition strategy based on specific institutional needs
- Partner with Senior managers in the work force planning process to determine present and future staffing needs
- Develop and implement service level agreements for resourcing and consultancy contracts management processes
- Prepare periodical management and board resourcing metrics and reports for all ILRI locations worldwide
- Employer branding and develop links with various recruitment partners

Managing Resourcing operations

- Lead, guide, develop the resourcing team and manage service delivery for the full-life cycle recruiting process
- Reviewing requirements for all new positions and ensuring that all job descriptions are evaluated and classified
- Liaise and communicate with the hiring managers in the recruitment process keeping them informed on recruitment efforts and the progress
- Proactively identify, source, and recruit candidates utilizing a variety of sources including, but not limited to, internet postings and search, direct sourcing, employee referrals, print media and networking
- Prepare various assessment tools for use in the recruitment process
- Manage the transition of staff from Post-doctoral to Scientist level
- Assist in relocation and on boarding of new staff

June 2013 – October 2013: HR Consultant for various organizations

Bridge International Academies (BIA)

April 2012 – May 2013: Acting HR Manager / Recruitment & HR Specialist (Consultant)

This role involved providing support in the implementation of the HR Strategy and managing the Recruitment function at Bridge International Academies; the world's largest education innovation company serving the 700 million families who live on less than \$2 USD per day.

Key Achievements

- Led the Recruitment team; to meet the needs of a fast expanding and dynamic company with varying recruitment needs, while headhunting for exceptional skills
- Successfully carried out a HR Audit to ensure Compliance and Data Integrity
- Coordinated the Salary Survey process in conjunction with PWC to pave way for a complete Job Evaluation process including job grading and salary banding in progress
- Developed Recruitment Policies and Strategies within the division
- Documented the Onboarding and Clearance Processes, ensuring a seamless integration of new employees and Exit of outgoing employees. This reduced loss in terms of time and resources
- Developed a Tracking system for Contracts, Probationary and Annual Review dates
- Initiated the Leave Management Automation process on SharePoint and Navision
- Significantly reduced the cost of Recruitment for the company by ensuring that Recruitments are handled in house and less of them through agencies
- Spearhead an Outplacement program with external Consultants to assist employees transitioning the Company through restructuring
- Successful Change Management

PKF Eastern Africa

January 2012 – to March 2012: Senior Human Resource Consultant

This role involved HR Service Delivery, Project Management, Business Development and Client Service at PKF Eastern Africa; a regional Audit and Advisory firm.

Key Achievements

- Staff Rationalization as a part of the due diligence process for a prospecting investor East African Portland.
- o Recruitment for various clients;
 - Finance Controller Mt. Elgon Orchards
 - Head of Finance Thomas Barnado Children's Home
 - Various Finance Positions Sight Savers International
 - Finance Manager Combined Warehouses

Sublime Concepts Management Consulting Ltd

January 2009 – December 2011: HR Consultant / Recruitment Manager

This role involved HR Service Delivery, Project Management, Business Development and Client Service at Sublime Concepts Management Consulting Ltd; a consulting firm providing Recruitment and HR Advisory services.

Key Achievements

- Successful recruitment of employees ranging from top management, middle level management and technical level employees and Head hunting for critical roles
- o Carried out GAP Analysis, HR Audits for various organizations
- Supported in; setting up systems, structures, and developed HR policies and strategies
- Successful implementation of Performance management Systems for, technical level, middle level to senior level employees
- o HR Generalist support for companies that outsourced their HR function

CERTIFICATIONS & PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIP

- ✓ Certified International Organizational Assessor **CEB SHL & HOGAN**
- ✓ Psychometrics Administrator and Personality Assessor CEB SHL & HOGAN
- ✓ Certified Competency Based Interviewer **A&DC UK**
- ✓ Project management Essentials (Franklin Covey) Raiser Resource Group
- ✓ Management Development Program Raiser Resource Group
- ✓ Trained Job Evaluator **Kon ferry Hay Group**
- ✓ Human Resource Business Partnering Rise & Learn
- ✓ Talent management & Succession planning Coaching and Mentoring International (CMI)
- ✓ Full member Institute of Human Resource Management (K)

PROFESSIONAL QUALIFICATIONS

East African School of Management

CPS – Certified Public Secretary (KASNEB)

EDUCATION BACKGROUND

2009 - 2011: University of Nairobi

Post Graduate Diploma – Human Resource Management **2001 – 2005: Catholic University of Eastern Africa**

Bachelor of Social Sciences

1997 - 2000: St. Anne's Lioki Secondary School

Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education

REFEREES:

Jedidiah Kuria Head of HR DB Schenker <u>Jedidah.Kuria@dbschenker.com</u> +254 725 752 029

+234 123 132 027

David Kabeberi
Partner - Consulting
PKF East Africa
dkabeberi@ke.pkfea.com
+254 204270000 /0732144000 / 0722 520
710

Emily Kerandi
Head of Learning & Development
International Livestock Research Institute (ILRI)

E.Kerandi@cgiar.org
+254 721 537 862

Edward Gathenya Director Sublime Management Concepts ltd edward@sublimeconceptsmgt.com + 254 722 678 404